The what factor. Let's do a quick assessment of what other people think of
your accent. How often during a day does someone ask you to repeat yourself? How
long does it take to give your email address? And how many times do you have to
spell your name? That's your what factor. But the real question is, how does this
affect you? How does it affect your working situation, your home life, your
life as a whole? Does it make you feel discouraged? Or does it encourage you to
change? Or does it make you feel like everyone else needs to change around you?
about someone who felt this way. We'll call her Mei Li. A Chinese professor was
studying English in the US and her instructor had suggested that, for
convenience, she Americanized the pronunciation of her name and she flew
into a rage. She excoriated him in a long email about how disrespectful this was to
5,000 years of her Chinese ancestors. The American instructor was stunned and passed
her on upstairs. The senior instructor set about finding out what was going on. To
say Dr. Li was linguistically rigid is a profound understatement. The instructor
would ask, but let's say you're at the DMV. The clerk doesn't know from Chinese
ancestors. Don't you just want them to catch your name the first time and to
process the transaction? No, she would declare, it's my name. The instructor
finally told her that they simply had to make a breakthrough. So her entire
homework would consist of leaving a voicemail with her name Americanized so it
would be easier to understand by any random person. She left eight to 10
identical Chinese sounding attempts. Finally, she left one that started with a
deep sigh and a deeper voice. My name is Mei Li. It was a thing of beauty.
Unfortunately, 30 seconds later, she left another very nasal one. My name is Mei Li.